Guide to the Papers of Jacques Judah Lyons (1813-1877), undated, 1705-1885, 1908, 1911-1914, 1917-1919, 1933, 1950 *P-15
American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA and New York, NY
Jacques Judah Lyons papers
undated, 1705-1885, 1908, 1911-1914, 1917-1919, 1933, 1950
Jacques Judah Lyons
Jacques Judah Lyons, hazzan, rabbi and community leader, was born in Surinam and emigrated to Philadelphia in the early 1800s. Minister of the New York Congregation Shearith Israel for 38 years, he gathered extensive materials on early Jewish history in the United States, Canada and the West Indies. His papers include manuscripts, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, notebooks, photographs and a Sansom ship's log book. Contains material relating to Jews in North and South America generally and more specifically to Congregation Shearith Israel and the Jews in New York, the Touro Synagogue and cemetery and the Jews in Newport, Rhode Island, Philadelphia and the West Indies. Also contains material relating to Jews in the wars of the United States, correspondence of the Jews with George Washington and items relating to Haym Salomon. Collection consists of manuscript material and five notebooks and three scrapbooks of Lyons. Contains also material not listed in calendar consisting of sermons by Lyons, a manuscript prayer book used in Surinam and a guide for religious ceremonies at Congregation Shearith Israel, as well as letters written during the Civil War period and correspondence relating to the personal life and career of Lyons.
12.05 linear feet (14 manuscript boxes; 3 oversize boxes (11.5 x 18 x 3.25), (16.5 x 20.5 x 3), (23 x 31.5 x 3))
P-15
American Jewish Historical Society
Biographical Note
Jacques Judah Lyons (1813-1877)
Jacques Judah Lyons, hazan, rabbi, and community leader, was born in Surinam, Dutch Guiana on Menahem 25, 5573 (August 25, 1813). His parents, Judah Eleazar and Mary Asser Lyons, had emigrated to Surinam from Philadelphia in the early 1800s. Jacques education was limited to the institutions the Dutch colony could afford; however, he spoke several languages in addition to Dutch, including Hebrew, English, German, and French and possessed a strong understanding of Spanish.
Jacques began his career as a hazan in Surinam in Congregation Nevie Shalom, a synagogue founded by Spanish-Portuguese Jews. In 1836 he left for Philadelphia, his parents' home state, and was hired within a few months by Congregation Beth Shalome of Richmond, Virginia. He served Beth Shalome for two years, winning the high esteem of the congregation. In 1839, following the death of Rev. Isaac B. Mendez Seixas, he was elected Seixas' successor as minister of Congregation Shearith Israel of New York City. He married Grace Nathan, daughter of Seixas Nathan and Sarah Mendes Seixas in 1842. Jacques and Grace were blessed with three children: Julius J., Sarah, and Alfred.
During his thirty-eight years of ministry, he became highly active in Jewish welfare and advocating Orthodox Judaism. He served as superintendent of the Shearith Israel's school, Polonies Talmud Torah; president of its benevolent society, Hebra Hased va-Emet; director of the Sampson Simson Jewish Seminary and Scientific Institute; and one of the founders of Jews Hospital, later renamed The Mount Sinai Hospital.
Jacques possessed a deep interest in Jewish history. In 1854, Jacques and Rabbi Abraham de Sola of Montreal collaborated in writing A Jewish Calendar for Fifty Years, a book that contained a comprehensive Jewish calendar, an essay on the Jewish calendar system, as well as historical information concerning Jewish communities in the United States, Canada, and the West Indies. Prior to 1861, and continuing to the end of his life, Jacques painstakingly gathered sources and information on United States Jewish history in the hopes of publishing his findings. He made copies of some of the documents he found, and also obtained papers from old families, such as Naphtali Phillips, Isaac Phillips, Joshua Phillips, Horatio Gomez, Joseph Nones, the Pesoa, and Judah Families. His family later destroyed a portion of his papers; one cannot but think of the treasures that may have been contained therein.
Jacques died at the age of sixty-three on Elul 4, 5638, shortly before Rosh Hashanah (August 15, 1877). His funeral services were held on August 15, 1877 in Shearith Israel, and were conducted by his successor Rev. Dr. Henry Pereira Mendes, Rev. Dr. Abraham De Sola of Montreal, Rev. Samuel M. Isaacs of Congregations Shaarai Tefilla of New York, and Rev. Sabato Morais of Congregation Mikve Israel of Philadelphia. His niece through marriage, Emma Lazarus, wrote the poem "Rosh Hashanah, 5638" in his memory. He is buried in the congregation's cemetery in Long Island.
References:
De Sola Pool, David and Tamar.An Old Faith in the New World: Portrait of Shearith Israel 1654-1954. New York: Columbia University Press, 1955, 178-182.
Publications of the American Jewish Historical Society (PAJHS), vol. 21 (1913), xxiii-xxviii; and vol. 27 (1920), 144-9.
Encyclopaedia Judaica. Jerusalem: Keter Publishing House, 1972. vol. 11, 626.
Scope and Content Note
The Jacques Judah Lyons Collection is a truly valuable source for researchers interested in early American and West Indies Jewish history. The collection primarily consists of material concerning the Shearith Israel Congregation, New York Jewish community, Touro Synagogue, Newport Jewish community, Philadelphia Jewish community, and West Indies Jewish communities. The collection also includes material relating to Jews who served in wars or military missions for the United States, correspondence of the Jewish leaders with George Washington, information concerning Haym Salomon, and a detailed log book of the Ship "Sansom."
The Jacques Judah Lyons Collection is composed of manuscripts, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, notebooks, log book and photographs. Materials are in fragile condition and must be handled very carefully. Certain items may be restricted from use due to fragility.
The collection is stored in a total of 14 manuscript boxes and three oversize boxes. Manuscripts are organized numerically:
Boxes 1-6A contain manuscripts
Boxes 7-10A, 12 contain scrapbooks, notebooks, and minute books
Box 11 contains correspondence pertaining to the Lyons Collection Committee.
It is believed that the current order of the collection was either specifically organized by the children of Jacques, or by Jacques himself. The reader is strongly urged to refer to the following volumes of the Publications of the American Jewish Historical Society, which categorize the manuscripts into broad subject areas, and offer summaries of each manuscript along with its reference number. These volumes are located in the reference collection in the reading room (call# E184.J5 A5). The volumes and their table of contents are as follows:
Volume 21 (Part I):
Earliest Extant Minute book of Congregation Shearith Israel, 1728-1760
Minute book of Congregation Shearith Israel, 1760-1786
Sketch of Congregation Shearith Israel by Naphtali Phillips (served for many years as clerk for the congregation), circa 1855
Address of Mordecai Manuel Noah (given at the laying of the cornerstone of the City of Ararat, 1825)
Volume 27 (Part II):
"Containing transcripts and summaries of the manuscripts embraced in the Collection, as well as the most important material selected from notebooks and scrapbooks of the late Rev. J.J. Lyons."
Manuscript Material:
Items relating to Congregation Shearith Israel, New York
Relating to Gershom Mendes Seixas
Relating to Rev. Jacques Judah Lyons
Miscellaneous items relating to Jews in New York
Items relating to the Seixas Family, New York
Items relating to the Jews of Newport
Items relating to Correspondence of Jews with George Washington
Miscellaneous items relating to Jews of North America
Log Book of the Ship Sansom
Receipt book of Congregation Shearith Israel, New York
Excerpts from the Gomez Ledger
Notebook Extracts:
Items relating to Congregation Shearith Israel, New York
Items relating to the Gomez Family, New York
Items relating to the Hays Family, New York
Items relating to the Moses and Levy Families, New York
Items relating to the Seixas Family, New York
Items relating to the Simson Family, New York
Items relating to the Solomons Family, New York
Miscellaneous items relating to Jews in New York
Items relating to the Newport Synagogue
Items relating to the Newport Cemetery
Items relating to masonry in Newport
Items relating to the Touro Family, Newport
Items relating to the Gould Family and the Jews of Newport
Miscellaneous items relating to the Jews of Newport
Items relating to Jews in Philadelphia
Items relating to Haym Salomon
Items relating to Jews in South America and the West Indies
Miscellaneous items relating to Jews in North America
Items relating to Jews in Wars of the United States and Correspondence with Washington
Excerpts from the Scrapbooks of Rev. J.J. Lyons
List of Pamphlets in the Collection (Note: These pamphlets are located in the Rosenbach Rare Book Collection, and have not been microfilmed as part of the J.J. Lyons Collection)
Please note that there are additional items in the collection that are not listed in either of the Publications of the American Jewish Historical Society volumes.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into six series as follows:
Series I: Manuscripts, undated, 1705, 1709-1880, 1933, 1950
Series II: Notebooks, undated, 1863, 1872
Series III: Scrapbooks, 1760-1786, 1812-1885
Series IV: Minute Book, undated, 1760-1786
Series V: Correspondence, undated, 1908, 1911-1914, 1917-1919
Series VI: Books, 1783-1804
Oversized Separated Material, 1730, 1738-1745, 1760, 1785, 1787, 1796-1797, 1803, 1817, 1819, 1826, 1829, 1839, 1843, 1846, 1871
Salomon, Haym, 1740-1785.; Washington, George, 1732-1799.; Congregation Shearith Israel (New York, N.Y.); Touro Synagogue (Newport, R.I.); Newport. Touro Synagogue.; New York. Congress.; Newport (R.I.); New York (N.Y.); Philadelphia (Pa.); Surinam.; West Indies.; Liturgy and ritual.; Rites and ceremonies.; Sermons.; Soldiers, Jews.; United States -- History.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Admission tickets; Articles; Bills of sale; Certificates; Contracts; Correspondence; Diaries; Drafts (documents); Eulogies; Hymns; Ketubahs; Legal notices; Lists; Log books; Manuscripts; Maps; Memorandums; Minutes; Newspaper clippings; Notebooks; Notes; Passports; Petitions; Photographs; Promissory notes; Publications; Receipts; Reports; Resolutions; Scrapbooks; Sermons; Speeches
Acquisition Information
The Lyons collection was donated to the American Jewish Historical Society in 1908 by Jacques Judah Lyons' children: Julius J. Lyons, Sarah Lyons, and Alfred Lyons.
Related Material
Papers of the Seixas Family of Newport and New York, P-60
Papers of the Gomez Family, P-62
Papers of Isaac Leeser, P-20
Papers of Aaron Levy, P-124
Levy family (New York, N.Y.) papers, P-455 Levy family (New York, Philadelphia and Baltimore) papers, P-120 Levy family (Newport, New York and New Orleans) papers, P-268
Paper of Judah Eleazer Lyons, P-121
Collection of Moses Haim Montefiore, P-189
Paper of the Moses Family, P-1
Papers of the Nathan Family, P-54
Papers of the Nones Family, P-5
Papers of the Touro Family, P-214
Papers of Uriah Phillips Levy, P-43
Records of Congregation Shearith Israel, I-4
Records of Mount Sinai Hospital, I-37
Records of the Association for the Free Distribution of Matzot to the Poor, I-106
Surinam Jewish Community Collection, I-94
Access Restrictions
Researchers Please Note: The Jacques Judah Lyons Collection is available on microfilm only.
Container List
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Series I: Manuscripts, undated, 1705, 1709-1880, 1933, 1950; 3.75 linear feet. Boxes 1-6A.
  This series contains 341 numbered documents, pertaining to the history of Jewish Americans in the earliest Jewish communities. These documents have been digitized and detailed descriptions are available by clicking the link. The rest of the manuscripts are unnumbered, and are miscellaneous items.
  - Celebration of Ararat Cornerstone Laying (MISSING), 1825 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Noah's Weekly Messenger (oversized, see Box #13), July 23, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - New York Enquirer, vol. 1, no. 3 (oversized, see Box #13), July 3, 1826 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter from Daniel I.M. Peixotto, regarding fasting, August 1, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Descendants of Benjamin Seixas, 1709-1850 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photos of Gomez coat of arms and other Gomez items, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1838-1839 documents relating to J.J. Lyons and his service to K.K. Beth Shalome, Richmond, Virginia (oversized, see Box #14), April 1838-August 1839 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Pennsylvania Packet and Daily Advertiser. Containing anecdote regarding Oliver Cromwell and the Jew (oversized, see Box #13), December 12, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Seixas family registers, 1721-1855 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Description of Beth Haim, Newport, and copy of deed, September 1872 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Consecration prayer for Mill Street or Crosby Street synagogues, 1818 or 1834 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters from N.H. Gould, Newport, regarding several matters. (see Publications of the American Jewish Historical Society, vol. 27, p. 190-191), 1854, 1856, and 1872 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Address to George Clinton, December 9, 1783 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Account of Isaac and Abraham de Peyster vs. Isaac Seixas and other papers (oversized, see Box #14), 1738-1745 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence with N.H. Gould, Newport, R.I., 1872-1873 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letter of Manuel Josephson to Moses Seixas regarding reading the Torah from a printed book, February 4, 1790 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letter from Simon Nathan to Mr. Harris, asking him to act temporarily as shochet, January 27, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letter to Aaron Levy from trustees K.K.S.I. regarding Beth Haim, February 21, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letter to K.K.S.I. from Moses and Simon Content, August 19, 1828 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Payment warrants, K.K.S.I., 1815-1816 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Promissory note to Aaron Levy, January 16, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Application to amend K.K.S.I. Constitution, July 11, 1833 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bill of Joseph Jacobs for baking matzah, April 10, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bill for various repairs to K.K.S.I., July 1817 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bill for masonry work, K.K.S.I., May 27, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Letter from Isaac Mendez Seixas introducing his son Gershom, to Joseph Simon, June 20, 1769 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Order of service for the 50thanniversary, Hebra Hesed V'emet, 1853: Order of service, 3rdanniversary of synagogue, 1821 (Hebrew), 1821, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Orders of service for special occasions, undated, 1818, 1820, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Photocopies of previous file of orders of service, undated, 1780, 1818, 1820, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 28a)
  - Dedication of new synagogue in Surinam (Dutch), May 5, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Program of special service on the emancipation of the slaves, Surinam (Dutch, translation provided from Publications of the American Jewish Historical Society), July 1, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Passport of Judah Lyons, July 31, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Letter of recommendation for J.J. Lyons from Isaac Leeser, February 22, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Certificate of J.J. Lyons discharge as hazan in Surinam with translation (Dutch, translation provided), November 5, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Application of J.J. Lyons to K.K.S.I. for hazan, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Resolution appointing J.J. Lyons Superintendent of Polonies Talmud Torah School, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Recommendation of J.J. Lyons from Surinam (Dutch and English translation), June 16, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Resolution of trustees regarding marriage of J.J. Lyons, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Condition and terms of leasing synagogue seats (in the Rosenbach Rare Book Collection), 1818 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Call for meeting regarding I.B. Seixas offering himself as hazzan, 1831 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Application to K.K.S.I. by Isaac Gomez for clerk, 1801 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Letter of Anne Seixas acknowledging $200 allowance, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Resolution of K.K.S.I. trustees regarding Irish famine, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Resolution of trustees regarding Thanksgiving Day, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Seixas report regarding the Sepher claimed by Isaac D. Lyons, August 1810 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Offering of Abraham Touro, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Letter from executors of Miss Pinto regarding legacy to Hebra Hased Va-Emet, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Statement of the funds of K.K.S.I.(oversized, see Box #14), 1803 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Petition of A.I. Abrahams, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Order of service arranged after the revolution, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Account of monies received for offerings, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Letter of K.K. Beth Elohim Charleston, regarding address to George Washington, 1790 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Application of Rachel Hays for a seat, May 14, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Simon Levy proposal to establish Hebrew school at K.K.S.I., September 3, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Letter of David G. Seixas to K.K.S.I., August 16, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Letter from Abraham Touro, August 31, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Blank form of bond used by trustees of K.K.S.I. for house and lot on Mill Street (unsigned), 1772 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Daniel VII:25 explained fixing time for Messiah. Found among papers of G.M. Seixas, 1783 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Resignation of B. Hart as treasurer and trustee, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Resolution of K.K.S.I. to Sir Moses Montefiore regarding his visit to Russia (oversized, see Box #13), September 17, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Ground Plan-Mill Street Synagogue (oversized, see Box #14), 1829, June 13, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Sermons, discourses, and epistolary opinions on religious matters by Gershom Seixas, undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Contract with John Moore for building house on Mill Street, December 2, 1790 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Receipt of Jacob Franks for silver from Curaçao towards building synagogue in New York (oversized, see Box #14), 1730 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Prayer composed in New York after the revolution (Hebrew, translation provided from Publications of the American Jewish Historical Society), 1784 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Subscription by members of K.K.S.I., July 26, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Call of meeting regarding shochet and circulars regarding Jacob Abrahams (in the Rosenbach Rare Book Collection), October 1811 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Request that remains of Mrs. Miriam Levy be buried in New York or Newport, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Papers relating to the Ladies Benevolent Society, undated, 1834, 1842-1866 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Portion of a manuscript of daily prayers in the handwriting of Abraham Isaacs, 1743 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Resolution regarding 2ndburial ground and consecration of same, undated (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Promissory note of Levi Solomon to Solomon Simson, New York (Not copied), October 8, 177(?) (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Isaac Levi's application to be shochet, August 20, 1794 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Registry of cases of circumcision by Abraham I. Abrahams in New York, June 1756 - February 1781 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Letter from Fanny Lazarus regarding seat for her son in the synagogue, December 19, 1798 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Names of boys and girls in the K.K.S.I school, March 8, 1795. Report of the School Committee, February 2, 1794, 1794-1795 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Boys and girls in religious school, handwriting of Rev. Gershom Seixas, March 8, 1795 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Application for assistance from Hanna Louzada, New Brunswick, N.J., November 9, 1761 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Subscription for building the first Mill Street Synagogue, Heshvan 15, 5489 (1728) (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Bond with list of papers belonging to trustees. Jacob Hart, Treasurer, undated (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Letter to trustees of K.K.S.I. from James Foster, regarding his desire to become a Jew (see Publications of the American Jewish Historical Society, v. 27, p. 44 for details), June 5, 1788 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Hebrew hymns and prayers after an earthquake, during the reign of George II (1727-1760) (Hebrew) (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Michael Hays' agreement with Alexander Zuntz regarding house owned by the congregation, October 22, 1783 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Petition of Aaron Salom of Jamaica to be hazan (oversized, see Box #14), February 11, 1760 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Letter of I.M. Gomez declining to act as arbitrator, May 4, 1796 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Memorandum of marriages and births in time of and by Rev. Gershom Seixas principally in his own handwriting. Compared with congregational record and omissions marked by J.J.L., 1804-1816 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Letter to congregation in Jamaica asking assistance to build a synagogue (Spanish, translation provided from Publications of the American Jewish Historical Society), 5489 (1729) (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Copy of English translation of prayer for peace during the revolution, with note of Rev. Gershom Seixas to Isaac Moses, undated (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Memo regarding loan of £300 made by G.W. Ludlow to the congregation, December 3, 1790 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Moses Costello's resignation as clerk of the trustees, September 10, 1794 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Citizenship certificate of Isaac Hayman (oversized, see Box #14), March 21, 1797 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - List of debts to K.K.S.I.(oversized, see Box #14), 5547 (1787) (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Permission of Parnas to marry Hart Levy's daughter, December 14, 1845 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Appointment of committee to superintend the baking of matzah, January 22, 1843 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Organization of the Board of Trustees, July 1, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Shochet's certificate, January 7, 1802 (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Opinion on Cohanim, in handwriting of Abraham H. Cohen, son of hazan Cohen of Philadelphia (see Publications of the American Jewish Historical Society, v. 27, p. 109), September 1825 (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - Certificate of Solomon Gompertz as shochet and bodek (Dutch), July 1800 (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - Resolution of the board on the wearing of the tallit, 1824-1827 (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - Letter from Rev. M.L.M. Peixotto regarding Rabbi Corcos of Curaçao, August 12, 1823 (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - Resolutions in regarding Harmon Hendricks, Naphtali Judah, Abraham Touro, and Washington Hendricks, July 24, 1823 (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Resolution prohibiting the performing of ceremonies at funerals of persons intermarried with Christians, 29 Adar I 5603 (1843) (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Query on the burial of persons married to Gentiles from the trustees answered, 1843 (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - Resolution directing the hazan not to offer any mitzvot for any individuals but those customary, October 27, 1836 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Letter in Hebrew appointing Haym Levy gabay for Jews in Hebron (Hebrew), 1763 (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - Ketubah (Hebrew) [Copy of]: Blank, with directions for filling it in on various occasions. (Original Deaccessioned by NMK in 1987), 5498 (1738) (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - Letter from the Parnassim of Curaçao to K.K.S.I. (Portuguese, translation provided from Publications of the American Jewish Historical Society), Sivan 5513 (1753) (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - Petition of Benjamin Jacobs to Hayman Levy to marry a non-Jew, circa 1775 (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - Letter to Abraham Pinto regarding insult to Parnas (oversized, see Box #14), 1796 (Box 2, Folder 108)